Finding Aid for Detroit Observatory (University of Michigan) records, 1860-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Detroit Observatory (University of Michigan) records 1860-2004 1994-2001
University of Michigan. Detroit Observatory.
0713 Bimu 2
The Detroit Observatory, an astronomical observatory on the campus of the University of Michigan, was the vision of University of Michigan President Henry Philip Tappan. He recognized the need for institutions of higher education to pursue scientific endeavors. Built in 1854, the Detroit Observatory was named after the Detroit residents who helped finance the building project. Extensive restoration work of the Observatory was completed in 1999.
29 linear feet and oversize material
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received from the Detroit Observatory (donor number 9529 ) in July 2005. Some architectural drawings were received through the Vice President for Research (donor number 5123 ) in 1997.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open without restriction.
In his inaugural speech of 1852, University of Michigan President Henry Philip Tappan stressed the need for institutions of higher education in America to pursue scientific endeavors in order to keep up with their European counterparts. Inspired by his speech, Detroit lawyer and former railroad businessman, Henry N. Walker approached Tappan, offering to help finance the construction of an astronomical observatory at the University of Michigan. Walker was able to secure funds from business acquaintances and friends, primarily Detroit residents. In 1854, an Observatory was constructed on the University of Michigan campus and named the Detroit Observatory in tribute to these Detroit benefactors. (For a detailed and rich account of the early history of the Detroit Observatory, researchers should consult the book of former Observatory director Patricia S. Whitesell entitled A Creation of His Own: Tappan's Detroit Observatory, 1998).
The Observatory flourished through the early twentieth century, enabling the construction of several additions to the original structure, including a director's residence and classroom and office spaces. During the latter half of the century, with a decline in use of the instruments and space along with the erection of new university buildings, these additions were demolished. Today, only the 1854 structure remains.
Throughout the 1960s and 1970s, the Observatory was mainly abandoned and the university proposed to demolish the building. A group of concerned citizens saved the building from destruction, and in 1973, the Detroit Observatory was placed on the National Register of Historic Places. Although the building was saved from destruction, the Observatory was in need of extensive restoration work. In 1994, the Office of the Vice President for Research and the History and Traditions Committee submitted a proposal to the University to restore the 1854 structure. Transferred to the new direction of the Office of the Vice President for Research, the Observatory was able to secure the necessary funds for restoration. From 1994 to 1999, the Detroit Observatory was significantly restored, from the restoration of the domes, telescopes, and interior furnishings to the addition of a bathroom and handicap accessible entrances and walkways. Under the new leadership of Patricia S. Whitesell, the Detroit Observatory opened its doors to the public, offering public tours (but no astronomic viewing program or other use of the historic telescopes), a lecture series, as well as many additional educational outreach activities. In 2005, the oversight of the Observatory was transferred to the Bentley Historical Library.
History of the Name
When the Observatory was constructed in 1854, it was named the Detroit Observatory to recognize the Detroit citizens who had donated funds for its construction. In 1931, the name was changed to the Observatory (Observatories) of the University of Michigan (Regents Proceedings, November 1931, p.809). In 1999, the identity was changed to the University of Michigan Detroit Observatory in tribute to the original name (Regents Proceedings, May 1999, p.335).
The Detroit Observatory record group includes administrative materials of the Observatory's later years (post-1994), including documentation on the Observatory's restoration project and materials encompassing the Observatory's publicity and outreach efforts. The collection also contains various historical documents and artifacts such as logbooks and records, photographs and other visual materials, motion pictures, architectural drawings, and publications. The collection includes all of the documents, artifacts, and records transferred to the Bentley Historical Library in 2005. Materials not physically transferred to the Bentley that remain in the Observatory (such as telescopes, clocks, and associated astronomical devices) have not been identified here, but documentation can be found listed in the various inventories and databases found in the administrative series.
This collection contains the following series: Administrative, Publicity and Outreach, Research, Historical, and Publications.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Detroit Observatory.; Astronomical observatories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Astronomy--United States.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Climate.; Historic buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Historic preservation--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Historic buildings--Conservation and restoration.
Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.
- Administrative 1994-2004, 5 linear feet
  The Administrative series (1994-2004, 5 linear feet) includes materials relating to the operation and functioning of the Detroit Observatory since 1994. This series includes an extensive inventory of photographs and descriptive records of the over three-hundred Detroit Observatory holdings; these are scientific instruments, historical photographs, publications, logbooks, and other miscellaneous artifacts and materials. The administrative series also includes correspondence, budget and fundraising documentation, meeting minutes, and materials documenting the day-to-day operation of the Observatory. A substantial portion of this series concerns the planning and implementation of the extensive restoration of the Observatory. For administrative materials prior to 1994, researchers should consult other Bentley collections, including the University of Michigan Observatory record group. The Observatory record group contains administrative material on the Detroit Observatory, including inventories, budgets, personnel, and account books from approximately 1908 to 1948.
  - Accessions
    - Accession Book, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - Artifacts
      - Artifact reference folders, 384 folders (Box 1)
      - Notes (Box 2)
      - Photographs, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Restoration
        - Photographs (Box 2)
        - Restoration photo log (Box 2)
    - Registration
      - Items 1-377, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - Catalog of items stored (Box 2)
        (not accessioned)
  - Astronomy Loan Agreement 1998 (Box 2)
  - Awards
    - American Association for State and Local History (AASLH) award 1999
      - Nomination, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Award (Box 2)
      - Press release (Box 2)
    - American Institute of Architects Award of Honor 2002 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Historic District Commission Preservation of the Year Award 1999 (Box 2)
    - Great Lakes Community Arts Award 2000-2001 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Historic Preservation Network Award 2000 (Box 2)
    - National Trust Award 2002 (Box 2)
    - Neubacher Award 1999 (Box 2)
    - Pyramid Award (Washtenaw Contractors Association) 1999 (Box 2)
  - Budget
    - General (Box 2)
    - Endowment 1999-2000 (Box 2)
    - 2001 (Box 2)
    - FY2000 (Box 2)
    - FY2001-2002 (Box 2)
  - Building
    - Carpenter's Shop 1999 (Box 2)
    - Dome Engineering 2004 (Box 2)
    - Jefferson Lighting 1999 (Box 2)
    - Landscaping 1999 (Box 2)
    - Maintenance Plan (Box 2)
    - Office Door 2002 (Box 2)
    - Paint Chart (Box 2)
    - Prairie Landscape 1998-1999 (Box 2)
    - Roof 2001 (Box 2)
    - Rotunda Storage (Box 2)
    - Space Survey 2004 (Box 2)
  - Building use
    - Astronomy Request (Seitzer comments) 1997 (Box 2)
    - Life Sciences Conference 2000 (Box 2)
    - LSA Request for Use 1994 (Box 2)
    - Use Plan (Box 2)
  - Bylaws 1997 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Buck, Dana 1994 (Box 3)
    - Hathaway, John 1995 (Box 3)
    - Hiltner, Ruth 1999 (Box 3)
    - Johnson, Kevin (Science Museum, London) 1998 (Box 3)
    - Kempf House 1996 (Box 3)
    - Krause, David 1995 (Box 3)
    - Landscape architects 1994 (Box 3)
    - Lindner, Rudi 1995 (Box 3)
    - Low Brows
      - General 1997 (Box 3)
      - Web pages newsletter 1998 (Box 3)
    - Miller, Freeman D. 1995-1999 (Box 3)
    - New York State Museum 1999 (Box 3)
    - Rosemergy, John 1998 (Box 3)
    - Seitzer, Patrick 1994-1999 (Box 3)
    - Victor Vaughan Society 1995-1999 (Box 3)
  - Director's Chronology files
    - July 1995-July 1999, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Executive Committee
    - General 1999-2000 (Box 3)
    - Meeting September 21, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Fundraising
    - Buhls 1997 (Box 3)
    - Gifts Account #304616, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Connable, Tenho
      - Bequest 1996-2000 (Box 3)
      - Lecture 2000 (Box 3)
    - Harnden (Robert) Gift 1996 (Box 3)
    - Hathaway (John) Bench 2002-2003 (Box 3)
    - Mayo, Dr. William L. 2003 (Box 3)
    - Miller, Mrs. Margaret Bequest 1997-2004 (Box 3)
    - Muir, Roy 2000 (Box 3)
    - Newsome, Gerald 2001 (Box 3)
    - Smith, Goff 2001 (Box 3)
    - Werner, Jeff (fundraising proposal) 2001 (Box 3)
    - Fundraising Appeal
      - November 1998 (Box 3)
      - November 1999 (Box 3)
    - Fundraising Brochure 1998 (Box 3)
    - Fundraising Letter 2001-2002 (Box 3)
    - Newsletter 2000 (Box 3)
    - Restoration
      - Brochure 1994 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1995-1996 (Box 3)
      - Fundraising Memo October 31, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Naming of the Observatory
    - Bollinger Communication 1998 (Box 3)
    - Regents Communications 1999 (Box 3)
  - National Landmark
    - History & Traditions Committee Plaque (Box 3)
    - Markers (Box 3)
    - Status (Box 3)
  - Program Coordinator Tasks (Box 3)
  - Restoration
    - 1970s
      - Various Documents on Restoration (Box 4)
      - John R. Hathaway Files (re: demolition) (Box 4)
      - Wallpaper (Box 4)
    - 1990s
      - Various Documents on Restoration (Box 4)
      - Restoration Proposal, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Advisory Group
        - General (Box 4)
        - History and Traditions Committee Presentation November 1996 (Box 4)
        - Meetings
          - September 13, 1994 (Box 4)
          - March 8, 1995 (architect selection)
            - Selecting an Architect (Box 4)
          - October 17, 1995 (Box 4)
          - July 25, 1996 (Box 4)
          - September 20, 1996 (Box 4)
          - October 21, 1996 (Box 4)
          - January 27, 1997 (Nick Steneck Comments, December 2, 1996) (Box 4)
        - NSF funding (Box 4)
        - Preservation Study and Schematic Design to Advisory Group (Box 4)
        - Advisory Group Disband (Box 4)
      - Architectural
        - Architectural Drawings (Box 4)
        - Catering/Parking (Box 4)
        - Plant Extension Committee (Box 4)
        - Regents Communication (Box 4)
        - Structural Assessment (Box 4)
      - Budget
        - $500K Budget (Box 4)
        - Observatory Spreadsheets (Box 4)
      - Construction
        - Construction Bid Opening (Box 4)
        - Construction Meetings, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Doug Hanna (University Architect) (Box 4)
        - J. C. Beal (Box 4)
      - Contractors
        - Furniture Sale (Box 4)
        - Mail Service (Box 4)
        - OSEH, Stain Analysis (Box 4)
        - Security/Keys (Box 4)
        - Shutters (Box 4)
      - Interior Design (Box 4)
      - Lighting (Box 4)
      - Paints
        - Paints (Box 4)
        - Paint Reports (Box 4)
      - Preservation Study
        - David Evans on the Period of Significance (Box 4)
        - Distribution and Comments (Box 4)
      - Quinn Evans
        - Architect Report (Box 4)
        - Proposal (Box 4)
        - Quinn Evans, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Stenecks
        - E-mail (Box 5)
        - Margaret "Peg" Steneck Request (Box 5)
        - Steneck Complaints (Box 5)
        - Margaret "Peg" Steneck Proposal (Box 5)
      - Storage
        - Items in Storage (Box 5)
        - Museum of Art (Box 5)
        - Storage Log (Box 5)
      - Telescopes
        - Collimating Telescopes (Box 5)
        - Fitz
          - Lens Cleaning (Box 5)
          - Christopher Ray Restoration Journal August 25, 1997-October 31, 1997 (Box 5)
        - Telescopes Committee (Box 5)
        - Telescopes Subcommittee (Box 5)
        - Warren Kutok (Box 5)
        - Christopher Ray (Box 5)
        - Weather Instruments (Box 5)
      - Work Orders
        - General (Box 5)
        - Upholstery Shop (Box 5)
        - Utilities (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Construction Sign (Box 5)
        - Disabled Student Services (Box 5)
        - Lead in Soil (Box 5)
        - Materials Safety Data Sheet (Box 5)
  - Reviews
    - 2000-2001 (Box 5)
    - Reviewers' Report 2001 (Box 5)
    - Unit Academic Assessment 2000 (Box 5)
    - Unit Review 2001
      - Master (Box 5)
      - Financial (Box 5)
      - Presentation (Box 5)
- Publicity/Outreach 1995-2005, 1 linear feet
  The Publicity and Outreach series (1995-2005, 1 linear ft.) contains information on Observatory lectures and tours, presentations, the Observatory's involvement in special events and projects, as well as information related to the website, including a 2005 web capture.
  - 1994-1999 various (Box 5)
  - Lectures and Tours
    - Lecture Series 2003-2004 (Box 6)
    - Photo Tour Captions (Box 6)
    - Schedules 2004-2005 (Box 6)
    - Self-guided Tour (Box 6)
  - Observatory Materials
    - Brochure and Bookmark (Box 6)
    - Historical Record (The Record column), 1997-1999 (Box 6)
    - Image of the Month 1999 (Box 6)
    - Newsletters 2000-2004 (Box 6)
    - Postcard (Box 6)
  - Photographs
    - Steven Graham Photography (Box 6)
    - UM Photo Services (Box 6)
  - Presentations
    - American Astronomical Society
      - 1996 (Box 6)
      - 1997 (Box 6)
    - Antique Telescope Society 1998 (Box 6)
    - Quinn Evans A.P.T. Presentation 1999 (Box 6)
    - Paul Courant Speech (Box 6)
    - Presentation Slides (Box 6)
  - Publications
    - Architecture Magazine (Box 6)
    - Articles (Box 6)
    - CAM article (Box 6)
    - Julie Ellison Poem (Box 6)
    - Paul Gross -- Weather records (Box 6)
  - Special Events
    - Detroit 300th
      - General (Box 6)
      - Theme Semester (Box 6)
    - Observatory Kick-off Event 1995 (Box 6)
    - Rededication 1999
      - General (Box 6)
      - Event (Box 6)
      - Invitation and Program (Box 6)
      - Transcript (Box 6)
    - Sesquicentennial 2004
      - General (Box 6)
      - Banner (Box 6)
      - Budget (Box 6)
      - Event (Box 6)
      - Expenses (Box 6)
      - Guests (Box 6)
  - Website
    - Website Capture 2005-2006
      - Online Archived version
      - Copy on CD-ROM (CD 53) (Box 3)
    - Formatting (Box 6)
    - Management (Box 6)
    - Virtual Museum (Box 6)
      (Arts of Citizenship grant)
- Research 2000-2001, 0.25 linear feet
  The Research series (2000-2001, 0.25 linear ft.) documents various historical research and background information on the Observatory, including museum labels and various student projects. Of special note is the Hall of Directors project, a compilation of background and historical information on each Observatory director, including portraits and documentation.
  - Rotunda Labels (Box 6)
  - Student Projects
    - Museum Methods 406 (Box 6)
    - Undergraduate Research Opportunity Program, Hall of Directors
      - General (Box 6)
      - BrÃ1/4nnow, Franz Friedrich Ernst (Box 6)
      - Watson, James Craig (Box 6)
      - Harrington, Mark Walrod (Box 6)
      - Hall, Asaph, Jr. (Box 6)
      - Hussey, William Joseph (Box 6)
      - Curtiss, Ralph Hamilton (Box 6)
      - Rufus, W. Carl (Box 6)
      - Curtis, Heber Doust (Box 6)
      - Maxwell, Alan D. (Box 6)
      - Goldberg, Leo (Box 6)
      - Miller, Freeman D. (Box 6)
      - Mohler, Orren C. (Box 6)
      - Hiltner, W. Albert (Box 6)
    - Web Architecture Course (Box 6)
    - Watson Medal 2001 (Box 6)
- Historical 1860-2004, 14 linear feet
  The Historical series (1860-2004, 14 linear ft.) consists of data, audiovisual materials, artifacts, and other collected records documenting the many uses and functions of the Observatory throughout its history. The series includes records of observations and research activities conducted at the Detroit Observatory as well as some observational data from as early as 1800. Some of these records were apparently held by the university Department of Astronomy, individual faculty members and private collectors. When the Observatory was reopened for educational and public programming activities in the 1990s, director Sandy Whitesell began acquiring historical records of the observatory. The Historical series has been organized by material type into three subseries: Records and Observational Data, Audiovisual Materials, and Artifacts.
  - Records and Observational Data
    The Records and Observational Data subseries consists of various sets of weather-related records and observational data recorded at the Observatory. Sets of anemometer (wind pressure), barograph (atmospheric pressure), and thermograph (temperature) records exist from the 1880s to the early 1900s. A set of logbooks that record various observations at the Observatory and data recorded from the Meridian Circle telescope are also part of this series. Other observation notebooks can be found in the University of Michigan Observatory record group in the Detroit Observatory subseries and the Observation charts and notebooks series.
    - Weather Records
      - Anemometer Record Sheets
        - Background (Box 7)
          (includes background documentation on significance and origin of weather records)
        - 1800-1886, 7 packets (Box 7)
        - 1887-1893, 7 packets (Box 8)
        - 1894-1899, 7 packets (Box 9)
        - 1900 part (January 1-June 8, 1900) (Box 9)
        - 1901-1903, 3 packets (Box 10)
        - 1904 and miscellaneous sheets (Box 10)
        - 1905 (Box 10)
        - 1908-1909, 3 packets (Box 10)
        - 1910-1915, 7 packets (Box 11)
        - 1922-1923, 2 packets (Box 24)
        - 1925 (Box 24)
      - Anemometer Readings and Reductions
        - 1880-1885 January (Box 12)
          (5 folders)
      - Barograph Readings and Reductions
        - 1880-1884 (Box 12)
          (6 folders)
      - Thermograph Readings and Reductions
        - 1880 December-1881 December (Box 12)
      - Meridian Circle Data Sheets (Box 12)
        (outsize)
      - Newspaper and other Clippings (Box 12)
      - Temperature Data 1881-1913 (Box 12)
        (probably compiled by Professor Hussey or under his direction)
      - Weather Signals
        - year unknown (Box 12)
        - 1886-1892, 7 folders (Box 12)
        - 1894 (Box 12)
      - Barograph and Thermograph Sheets
        - 1880-1886 (Box 25)
          (7 packets)
        - 1887-1890 (Box 26)
          (4 packets)
        - Miscellaneous 1884-1887 (Box 26)
          (2 packets)
      - Observing Records for the Spotz-Ailtner Spectrograph 1970-1972 (Box 26)
        (accession no. 129)
        (outsize, listed in Box 15)
    - Log books
      - 37 1/2" Observing Books
        - no. 1 (1911)-no.30 (1933), 30 volumes (Box 13)
          (accession no. 118)
        - 1974 (Box 13)
          (accession no. 124)
        - no.31 (1933)-no.59 (1968), 29 volumes (Box 14)
      - Dean B. McLaughlin Observations of Spectra of Novae
        (accession no. 121)
        - no. 1-no. 2, 2 volumes (Box 15)
        - no. 4 (Box 15)
        - no. 5 (Box 15)
        - no. 7 (Box 15)
        - 2 unidentified volumes (Box 15)
          (could be numbers 3, 6, or 8, accession nos. 118 or 121)
      - Log Book for New Telescope 1969-1971 (Box 15)
        (accession no. 257)
      - Observing Record, Spotz Spectrograph, 52" Telescope May-July 1970 (Box 15)
        (accession no. 258)
      - Observing Records for the Spotz-Ailtner Spectrograph March 23, 1970-June 18, 1972 (Box 26)
      - Ross Four-inch Camera, Record of Observations, book 1 October 1927-June 1949 plates 1-607 (Box 15)
        (accession no. 126)
      - Book 2, Notes on Be Spectra (Box 15)
        (accession no. 125)
      - Calibration Procedure and Results of Calibration of the Wedge Slit of the Calibrating Spectrograph 1949 (Box 15)
        (accession no. 122)
      - R. H. Curtiss, six-inch Photographs 1909-1912 (Box 15)
        (accession no. 123)
      - Observations, Probably of Heber D. Curtis
        - 1929 (Box 15)
          (accession no. 188)
        - 1932 (Box 15)
          (accession no. 186)
  - Audiovisual Materials
    Photographs, lantern slides, negatives, etchings, and sunspot maps can be found in the visual materials subseries. These materials document various astronomical subject matter, people, the Detroit Observatory, astronomical observations (including solar flares, planets, stars, and Halley's Comet) other observatories around the world, and scientific instruments.
    Motion pictures in the form of reel-to-reel film and VHS videocassettes contain historic footage of various observations and Observatory construction and restoration projects.
    - Photographs
      - Historical Photographs, 2 volumes (Box 16)
      - Observatory Scrapbook, 1 volumes (Box 16)
        (includes historical photographs, mostly copied from Bentley photographs of the Observatory, with captions)
      - Restoration Photographs, 1 volumes (Box 16)
      - Stephen Graham Photography 1999, 1 volumes (Box 16)
      - Astronomical Subjects
        - Comet Tagago-Sato-Soshaka (Box 17)
          (accession no. 327)
        - Milky Way Galaxy
          - [Undescribed] (Box 17)
            (accession no. 229)
          - [Undescribed] (Box 17)
            (accession no. 141)
        - Monochromatic Picture of the Corona (red line) Portion of the Coronal Spectrum (Box 17)
          (accession no. 265)
        - Solar Images
          - [untitled] (Box 17)
            (accession nos. 329, 330, 333, 336-337)
          - Passage d'une protuberance sur le disque solaire (Box 17)
          - Eruption chromospherique du 25 juillet 1946 (Box 17)
          - Groupe de taches solaires 22 juin 1885 (Box 17)
        - Spectra
          - Spectra from three different dates in 1918, 1950
            (accession no. 271)
            - Negatives (Box 17)
            - Prints (Box 17)
          - Spectrum taken with McMath Solar Telescope (Box 17)
            (accession no. 328)
        - Transit of Mercury over Sun May 11, 1937 (Box 17)
          (accession no. 264)
      - Conferences and Gatherings
        - American Astronomical Society Meetings
          - 1922 Yerkes Observatory (Box 17)
            (accession no. 297)
          - 1924 US Naval Observatory (Box 17)
            (accession no. 137)
        - Undated Conference?, Observatory, Nantucket, MA (Box 17)
          (accession no. 227)
      - Detroit Observatory
        - Observatory from Northwest circa 1930 (Box 17)
          (accession no. 228)
        - Photograph Reprints (Box 17)
          (accession no. 183)
        - Slides of Exterior 1976, 3 slides (Box 17)
      - Observatories and Scientific Instruments (other)
        - Allegheny Observatory, PA
          - (accession no. 226) (Box 17)
          - (accession no. 324) (Box 17)
        - Cerra Tololo Interamerican Observatory (near Santiago, Chile) (Box 17)